

BIOINFORMATICIAN

Hamilton ON, Canada

□ (+1) 289-700-4400 | Image: Inishanth.merwin@gmail.com | Image: Image:

"A researcher tackling biology one keystroke at a time."

Summary.

Current consultant for Adapsyn Biosciences as their resident machine learning and genomic data specialist. Over four years working in academic and industrial biological research environemnts and two years specializing in informatics solutions. A problem solver with linux, python and a slew of machine learning algorithms as a toolbox for building solutions to the challenging tasks at hand.

Work and Research Experience_

Adapsyn Bioscience

Hamilton, ON, Canada

GENOMICS & DATA SCIENCE CONSULTANT

Sep. 2016 - Current

- Developed metabolomic pipeline to translate raw data, along with user inputted metadata, into a query-able format for database import and visualization. Built using OOB principles in Java 8.
- Assembled bacterial genomes using hybrid sequencing data, and subsequently analysed data to reveal potentially novel antibiotics

McMaster University

Hamilton, ON, Canada

GRADUATE RESEARCH STUDENT, SUPERVISED BY DR. NATHAN MAGARVEY

May. 2015 - Current

- · Built an analytical toolkit for rapid isolation and characterization of novel peptidic small molecules using genomic and metabolomic datasets.
- Ported PRISM, a genomic analysis software for translating genomic data into small molecule predictions, onto 300-core HPC infrastructure to scale usage for public users.
- · Built interactive web visualizations for viewing high dimensional mass spectrometry and genomic data using D3.js.

McMaster University

Hamilton, ON, Canada

SENIOR THESIS STUDENT, SUPERVISED BY DR. ELIZABETH WERETILNYK

Sep. 2014 - May 2015

- · Developed a multifaceted project in order to build a thorough understanding of Eutrema salsugineum's responses to potassium deficiency.
- · Effectively presented up to date findings at local and external conferences to engage and learn from meaningful discussions.

The Hydropothecary Corporation

Gatineau, QC, Canada

STUDENT RESEARCHER

May. 2014 - Aug. 2014

- Conducted primary and secondary research in order to provide proper advisory services for the large-scale production of medical marijuana with consistent and optimal cannabinoid profiles.
- Worked alongside a team to successfully plan and harvest the first annual production of medical marijuana within a 650 m² greenhouse.

Algaeneers Inc.

Hamilton, ON

STUDENT RESEARCHER

June 2013 - April 2014

- Gained practical experience with novel biochemical techniques to develop high-level recombinant protein expression in a microalgae systems.
- · Developed tools to assess transformation efficacy through transcriptional and functional assays.

Education

McMaster University

Hamilton, ON, Canada

M.Sc. in Biochemistry and Biomedical Sciences

May. 2016 - Current

 $\bullet \ \ \text{Awarded graduate research scholarship (\sim45K$) acknowledging impact of research completed during studies. } \\$

Seneca College

Toronto, ON, Canada

GRADUATE CERTIFICATE IN BIOINFORMATICS

Sep. 2015 - May. 2016

· Graduated with President's Honour list for outstanding academic achievements.

McMaster University

Hamilton, ON, Canada

B.H.Sc. specializing in Biochemistry and Biomedical Science

Sep. 2011 - May. 2015

· Received McMaster Honour and Dean's Honour list awards for outsanding academic transcripts.

November 23, 2017 Nishanth J. Merwin · Résumé

Publications

- Mousa WK, Athar B, Merwin NJ, Magarvey NA. Antibiotics and specialized metabolites from the human microbiota. Natural Product Reports 2017; doi:10.1039/c7np00021a
- Skinnider MA, Merwin NJ, Johnston CW, Magarvey NA. PRISM 3: expanded prediction of natural product chemical structures from microbial genomes. Nucleic Acids Research 2017; doi:10.1093/nar/gkx320
- Skinnider MA, Johnston CW, Edgar RE, Dejong CA, <u>Merwin NJ</u>, Rees PN, et al. Genomic charting of ribosomally synthesized natural product chemical space facilitates targeted mining. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences; 2016; doi:10.1073/pnas.1609014113

Honors & Awards

2017 Excellence in Oral Presentation Award, Faculty of Health Sciences Plenary

Hamilton, ON
University of

2016 **2nd Place**, iGEM Bioinformatics Hackathon

Toronto